Today's דף Daf is ל"א Lamed Aleph 31, 44th day in the
עומר. Omer. And we pick up three lines down from the top
after the parenthesis. And we're dealing again with all these questions about
thoughts of פיגול Piggul and if another thought is mixed up, a
thought of חוץ למקומו, Chutz L'komo, then it doesn't become פיגול. Piggul.
And then this interesting and then the position of רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda that actually he thinks that no, actually once it's פיגול Piggul
it doesn't stop being it, certainly not by a thought. You would
have to have the bad thought first and make it invalid and
then it can't become פיגול. Piggul. But רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
if the bad thought came after, it did not make a problem.
And we had a whole fun time yesterday figuring out how do
you define, you know, according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda whether it's
one thought or two thoughts and so on. כזית וכזית, K'zayis u'k'zayis,
one עבודה, Avoda, two עבודות, Avodas, etc. Okay, anyway, but keeping with
that idea we continue the following discussion: איתמר. Itmar.
חצי זית חוץ לזמנו. Chatzi zayis chutz lizmano. Now this is even
working what we're sort of going to say within the רבנן, Rabbanan,
okay?
That any other bad thought will prevent it from becoming פיגול. Piggul.
חצי זית חוץ לזמנו וחצי זית חוץ למקומו וחצי זית חוץ לזמנו.
Chatzi zayis chutz lizmano v'chatzi zayis chutz limkomo v'chatzi zayis chutz lizmano.
So here the person has these three thoughts. I'm going to eat
a half of a כזית K'zayis in the wrong time, then a
half of the wrong place, and then he thinks again, oh now
I'm also going to eat another half in the wrong time. Now,
if he had said I'm going to eat a full כזית K'zayis
at the wrong time and a half of a כזית K'zayis in
the wrong place, that would not prevent it from being פיגול Piggul
because you wouldn't say, oh, this is even within the רבנן, Rabbanan,
forget רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Oh, another bad thought prevents it from
being פיגול. Piggul. But a thought about a half of a כזית
K'zayis is not meaningful. Okay, the only thought that's meaningful is a
thought about a כזית, K'zayis, a full אלף's Aleph worth. So had
he said I'm going to eat a כזית K'zayis in the wrong
time and then a second later he said I'm going to eat
a half a כזית K'zayis in the wrong place. If he said
a כזית K'zayis in the wrong place, okay, it's another bad thought,
it prevents it from being פיגול. Piggul. But if he said a
half a כזית K'zayis it would not. A half a כזית K'zayis
thought is not meaningful. Okay, but here's what he said: first he
said, let's see, I guess he's
drawing stuff, right?
Which way should I go? Left to right, I guess. I'm going
to go right to left. Okay.
Half of a
כזית K'zayis חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano.
In this case makes no difference because it's both
half חוץ, chutz, no it doesn't make a difference, I mean מקומו.
komo. Oh, let me add right to left. Okay, and half
חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano. So in this case, had he had
these two first and then this, it would have been פיגול. Piggul.
But when he got up to
here, the קרבן korban was already פסול passul because then he had,
that's the principle of צירוף tzeiruf that we learned in our משנה,
Mishna, we learned it out from יהיה. yihyeh. Once he got up
to here, he had a thought about a full כזית K'zayis worth
to do something wrong with it. Not the same wrong thing, but
some combination of wrong things. So the הלכה halacha is had he
stopped right here, the קרבן korban would have been פסול, passul, if
you remember that in the משנה. Mishna. So should we basically say,
okay, the קרבן's korban already פסול, passul, you can't now make it
פיגול? Piggul? Or should we say, you know, these two only joined
up because they were halves and they didn't have anywhere else to
go, but now we sort of step back and we say really
it's a thought about a whole כזית K'zayis of פיגול Piggul and
it's פיגול, Piggul, okay? We reassess. And we say that that thought
about a half of a כזית K'zayis doesn't mean anything. So that's
the question. איתמר. Itmar. חצי זית
חוץ לזמנו וחצי זית חוץ למקומו וחצי זית חוץ לזמנו. Chatzi zayis
chutz lizmano v'chatzi zayis chutz limkomo v'chatzi zayis chutz lizmano. אמר רבא:
Amar Rava: ויקץ כישן הפיגול. Vayikatz kiyoshen ha'piggul. You've got to say
it's such a strange, whatever, it's like a terse phrase. And it
wakes up like a sleeping person, the פיגול. Piggul. The פיגול Piggul
wakes up, okay. Now, תוספות Tosafos makes a point, רש"י Rashi borrows
a phrase which is very similar phrase, which is חוזר ונעור, chozer
v'nei'or, it wakes up again. But תוספות Tosafos says it's not exactly
the same. חוזר ונעור Chozer v'nei'or is, where does he begin
with, well you're dealing with real physical objects. Okay, I've got my
chicken soup here, and biting in my chicken soup I dropped, you
know,
let's say this is 60 units of chicken soup and I dropped
a half of a unit of חזיר. chazir. Okay, so it's בטל.
batel. And then afterwards I drop another half of a unit of
חזיר. chazir.
Then it wakes up the other half unit, it's חוזר ונעור, chozer
v'nei'or, that's the question, but let's assume for now it does, okay,
as opposed to קמא קמא בטל. kama kama batel. Anyway, it wakes
it up and now I say I have a whole, not a
whole כזית, k'zayis, a whole unit of חזיר chazir and it's not
בטל. batel. Okay, so it's a similar idea, right? It wakes it
up. רש"י Rashi sort of uses that language. תוספות Tosafos just says,
okay fine, it's analogous but it's not the same because there's an
important difference. The important difference is here at the end of the
day you actually have physically a full unit, okay? Whereas here you're
just dealing with thoughts, you know? They're just thoughts, okay? So you
don't have like a full unit now of thought present in the
ether somewhere. Okay, these are just thoughts. So it's not exactly the
same. And you should have said this was a thought that invalidated,
this is a separate thought, we don't step... Step back and let's
re- let's take a bigger picture about it and say you had
a thought about a כזית kzayis of פיגול. pigul. Anyway, that's the
question. But רבא Rava says yes, you do say that here, even
though it became פסול, pasul, you step back and re-evaluate and you
say no, you have a more natural combination of the חוץ לזמנו
chutz l'zmano thoughts and therefore it's פיגול. pigul. Okay, so that's what
רבא Rava says. ויקץ קץ הפיגול. Vayikatz ketz hapigul. For רב המנונא
Rav Hamnuna אמר amar ערב מחשבות הוי. erev machshavos havei. No, the
thought about חוץ למקומו chutz l'mkomo is an ערב מחשבות erev machshavos
and it's, you know, it's an extraneous thought that invalidates and it
does not become פיגול pigul because it already became פסול. pasul. Now,
presumably his reason is that it already became פסול. pasul. What would
be- sorry, if it's getting too complicated- what would be if your
thought here was about a quarter of a כזית kzayis of חוץ
למקומו? chutz l'mkomo? So it would have occurred between the חוץ לזמנו
chutz l'zmano thoughts, but it would not have made the קרבן korban
פסול pasul because it wasn't yet a full כזית. kzayis. Presumably there
he would say- he would agree that it's פיגול. pigul. It's not
just that there's another thought in there, presumably. Presumably it's that with
that other thought it already became פסול. pasul. And since with that
other thought it already became פסול, pasul, it doesn't become פיגול pigul
again. That's the other opinion. Okay, ערב מחשבות הוי. erev machshavos havei.
אמר רבא Amar Rava מנא אמינא לה? Mena amina lah? Where do
I know this from?
דתנן Detnan כביצה אוכל ראשון kebeitzah ochel rishon וכביצה אוכל שני. v'kebeitzah
ochel sheni. Now, you have an egg's worth of food, an egg's
worth of food is what you need for it to be- make
other things טמא, tamei, maybe even for it to become טמא, tamei,
I'll get to that later. Anyway, so you have one egg's worth
of food, let's say dough, let's make it an easy scenario. I
just take an egg. An egg? No, but it's easier dough as
you'll see in a minute, that touched a נבלה. neveilah. So it's
one- it's, you know, it's level one of טומאה. tumah. Then you
have another כביצה kebeitzah of food that touched something that already became
טמא, tamei, that touched, you know, I don't know, let's even say
that touched the first piece of dough, okay? So this separate second
piece of dough is a שני, sheni, it's two degrees- is two
degrees removed. Everybody with- you got one piece of dough that's a
ראשון לטומאה rishon l'tumah and one piece of dough that's a שני
לטומאה. sheni l'tumah. All right? שבוללן זה בזה. shebelalan zeh bazeh. You
have a question there? No. שבוללן זה בזה. shebelalan zeh bazeh. Now,
you mixed them together to make a two כביצה kebeitzah piece of
dough.
So, ראשון, rishon, this stuff if it touches something, it has the
power of a ראשון rishon because within this bigger piece of dough,
there's a full כביצה's kebeitzah worth of
ראשון לטומאה rishon l'tumah and therefore it can make something else into
a שני. sheni. So you get the scenario? Okay. Here's your big
piece of dough. I'll do it after it's been mixed up.
Somewhere in here combined, okay, because it's all mixed together, is stuff
that's a ראשון. rishon. A whole כביצה's kebeitzah worth of ראשון. rishon.
And other stuff in here also spread out, okay, I mean, whatever,
it's- is stuff that's a שני. sheni. So in this big piece
of dough, like an amoeba or something...
I'm just thinking...
In this big piece of dough, you have a כביצה's kebeitzah worth
of a ראשון. rishon. When this big piece of dough touches, I
don't know, an apple, you have a- you have a ראשון לטומאה
rishon l'tumah in here touching an apple, and the apple becomes a
שני. sheni. Okay? Fine. Because you have the full amounts of both.
Now,
ראשון. rishon.
Would that work if you had like ten ביצים beitzim of שני
sheni and one כביצה kebeitzah of ראשון?
rishon? That's a- yeah, that's an interesting question about ביטול, bitul, but
we're not- would you say ביטול bitul by טומאה? tumah? But let's
not worry about that now. חילקן, Chilkan,
זה שני וזה שני. zeh sheni vezeh sheni. Now, you went ahead
and you cut them in half. Okay? Now, if you cut them
in half and you have one of these halves touching something, it's
only going to be a שני. sheni. You know why? Because in
any one half of this, you don't have a full כביצה kebeitzah
worth of a ראשון. rishon. You have a half a כביצה kebeitzah
worth of ראשון. rishon. So you need a כביצה kebeitzah to be
ראשון? rishon? Assume you need- yes, you do. You need a כביצה
kebeitzah to be מטמא. metamei. Okay? We're talking about being מטמא metamei
something else. So at any half of it, okay, you have a
half a כביצה kebeitzah of ראשון, rishon, half כביצה kebeitzah of a
שני. sheni. So you don't have enough of a ראשון. rishon. What
you have is a full כביצה, kebeitzah, I mean, the principle is
if you have a half a כביצה kebeitzah of ראשון rishon and
half a כביצה kebeitzah of a שני sheni and they combine, it's
like a כביצה kebeitzah of a שני. sheni. Okay? It goes to
the common denominator. Okay, but so if you split it in half,
you have a half of a כביצה kebeitzah of each in each
half, so it operates like a שני, sheni, there's not enough of
a ראשון rishon in any
half. זה שני וזה שני. zeh sheni vezeh sheni. החזר ועירבן, Hechezir
v'irvan, ראשון. rishon. But if you were to put them back together,
even though you have a half and a half, it would be
a ראשון. rishon.
Okay, ראשון הוי. rishon havei. מאי? Mai? Now, we even- we don't
even have to infer that. It's explicit. מדיקתני סיפא, Midekatani seifa, נפל
זה בעצמו וזה בעצמו nafal zeh be'atzmo vezeh be'atzmo על כיכר של
תרומה, al kikar shel trumah, פסלוה. pasluha. Okay, let's say this half
fell on תרומה. trumah. תרומה Trumah can become a שלישי. shlishi. When
תרומה trumah becomes a שלישי shlishi it's called פסול. pasul. This half
falls on תרומה, trumah, and then the next half falls on תרומה.
trumah. It only remains a שלישי. shlishi. By the time the first
half came it became a שלישי, shlishi, the next half falling doesn't
do anything else. Still at each time it's only touching something that's
a שני. sheni. But אם נפלו שניהם im naflu shneihem נפלו שניהם
כאחד, naflu shnehem ke'echad, if they both, these two halves fell on
a piece of תרומה, Terumah, even if they didn't fall simultaneously, if
one fell and stayed there, and then the next fell, then at
that moment you have a full כביצה kebeitzah of a ראשון לטומאה
rishon letumah touching the תרומה, Terumah, half of a ביצה beitzah here
and a half of a ביצה beitzah here, and then it makes
the תרומה Terumah into a שני. sheni. Okay, so נפלו שניהם כאחד,
naflu shnehem ke'echad,
עשה שני. asa sheni. Okay, so now how is that a proof
to רבא? Rava? So the proof is, is that look, this stuff
in here got, it's sort of like it got mixed up with
something else. This stuff here was a half of a ביצה beitzah
of, what did you have in this half? You had a half
of a שני sheni and you had a half of a ראשון.
rishon. Okay, sort of like a half and a half. Okay, so
this then when it got back in touch with its origins, okay,
you know, when it got back in touch with the other half,
they're both sitting on the piece at the same time, you don't
say it's lost its identity of a ראשון. rishon. It's able to
wake up and reconnect with the ראשון rishon in the other half
and to make a full כביצה. kebeitzah. Okay, so that's why he
says here too it can wake up. Now part of the problem
of making this analogy is what תוספות Tosafot says, which is like
this case, this case is they're both physically there. At that moment
it's not like, you know, thoughts which pass in time and then
don't exist anymore. At that moment sitting on the piece you have
a half of a ראשון rishon and a half of a ראשון
rishon and you have a whole ראשון rishon touching this תרומה. Terumah.
Okay, I mean as long as you don't say ביטול, bittul, which
is Michael's question, there's not much of a חידוש chiddush there, you
have a half of each. Here the stuff is a thought that
sort of goes out of existence,
you
know. Also for רבא Rava it's
along with it being non-physical is an element of time that maybe
it puts it into a different category.
Right, that's right, so thank you for pointing that out. I was
saying that but thank you for sort of pointing, you know, focusing
on that. Right, here when they're both sitting on the תרומה Terumah
at this time, there's one moment in time that you have a
full כביצה kebeitzah of ראשון, rishon, whereas here this stops existing in
time, this stops existing in time, is that what you're sort of
saying?
Well, I was thinking also that the question of פיגול pigul has
to do with the time sequence. Like you know in music, music,
like a symphony, you know, it's different, motion picture.
Right, meaning here the principle is you already were מבטל mevatel it,
right, it's not just like you didn't have sufficient. Right, like yeah
I agree, like there was already, exactly, there's a lot of differences.
So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is, then there's going
to be a debate רש"י Rashi תוספות Tosafot what the גמרא's Gemara
answer means. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so the, the analogy is, is strange, but let's go with
it. ורב המנונא אמר, veRav Hamnuna amar, רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna would
say back, התם איכא
שיעורא הכא ליכא שיעורא. hatam ika shiura hacha leka shiura. There there's
a שיעור, shiur, here there's no שיעור. shiur. Now what does it
mean that there, what does it mean? So what רש"י Rashi says
it means is,
here you started before you had these two mixtures, you started with
one, with a כביצה kebeitzah of each. Okay,
then they got mixed up, then they split, then they recombined. Since
this thing started as a full, or this started as a full
כביצה kebeitzah of ראשון, rishon, it's easier, it doesn't lose its identity
and it's easier after it split and then whatever for it to
recombine and to re-become a full כביצה kebeitzah of a ראשון. rishon.
Whereas here you only, you started with a half. And because you
started with a half, it's harder for it to combine back to
combine now with that other half.
Okay, it just depends on how much you start with pretty much.
Well, if you start with the full amount and you separate it
then it's more easy for it to recombine, whereas if you only
start with a half then it sort of stops here and it
doesn't find. That's the way רש"י Rashi reads it. תוספות Tosafot reads
it that we don't mean that this started with a full שיעור.
shiur. What we mean is, is that this, is that
this has a full like שיעור shiur present together, there's one full
amount of each. Real תוספות Tosafot says we're started talking about this,
about the שני לטומאה, sheni letumah, okay, because since this is a
full שיעור, shiur, it's sort of like, you know I was sort
of thinking about this about like how,
like in, what is it, like is it in DNA or whatever
when those things get, anyway, what are those things that they, now,
the receptors in your body, the things that sort of, oh I
can't even remember. Anyway, nobody knows what I'm talking about. I know
what you mean. No no no no, when, you know when you
have like, when, you know certain things bond with certain receptors and
then they prevent other stuff from bonding with it or whatever. Anyway,
so, so what תוספות Tosafot says is, because this is a half
of a כזית, kezayit, it bonds more tightly with this because each,
because it's sort of like it like needs that, you know, it's
like it's incomplete and it needs it, so they bond more tightly.
So when this other thing appears, it doesn't go away because this...
is a very tight bond. Okay, so your focus is sort of
on the middle part. Okay, if it's incomplete, it creates a tighter
bond and then you can't ignore it and recombine it, whereas here
because this is complete, it doesn't need something else to complete it,
okay, so to hold maybe an analogy for marriage, right, two halves,
whatever. So since it doesn't need something as much to complete it,
it's more it's easier for it to walk away and then this
thing can like, you know, recombine. Anyway, so for רש"י Rashi the
point is that this started with the full amount and therefore it's
easier for it to become a full amount and for that's the
full שיעור shiur that תוספות Tosfos says the thing that's getting in
the way here it's a full amount so it's easier for it
to separate out. Whereas here the thing getting in the way is
a half amount so it bonds in a more tight way, okay,
ignoring the whole difference between thought versus physical. All right, moving on.
All right, הכא ליכא שיעור. hacha leka shiur. אמר רב המנונא מנא
מני לה Amar Rav Hamnuna mina milo so that was רבא's Rava
attempt to prove it. Let's see רב המנונא's Rav Hamnuna proof of
it that actually it does recombine. Okay, מנא מני לה דתנן האוכל
שנטמא באב הטומאה ושנטמא בוולד הטומאה מצטרפין זה עם זה לטמא בקל
שבשניהם. mina milo detnan ha'ochel she'nitma be'av hatuma veshenitma bevlad hatuma mitztarfin
ze im ze letame bekala shebishneihem. Okay, so that's pretty much the
same point. You have food that became טמא tamei with an אב,
av, so it is a ראשון, rishon, an אב av is the
source like a נבילה, neveilah, so the food that became טמא tamei
through an אב av is now ראשון, rishon, first degree removed. And
you have food that became טמא tamei through a ולד, vlad, a
already a derivative, a ראשון, rishon, so it becomes a שני, sheini,
okay,
so you have a ראשון rishon and
a שני sheini combine.
Okay, מאי לאו, mai lav, now, if they combine, okay, that's basically
this scenario, okay, you have basically right you have a half of
a כזית kezayis of ראשון rishon and you have a
half of a כזית kezayis of שני sheini and they combine to
make a to act as a שני. sheini. Okay, so what does
that prove? So what he says is it sounds he wants to
infer since it just says they combine presumably it means that they
combine and that's it, that's the end of the story. מאי לאו
mai lav doesn't that not mean so it's pretty much a similar
type of an argument except trying to prove it the other way,
but the same analogy. Okay, מאי לאו אף על גב
דהדר מליה mai lav af al gav dehadar malyei
doesn't this mean even if then you went ahead and added another
half of the ראשון rishon it would still continue to operate just
as a שני. sheini. It says these combine to operate as a
שני, sheini, okay, so presumably he says it means that they combine
even if right presumably that's the end of the story and even
if you put this thing it would still remain a שני, sheini,
okay, so that's my proof, all right, not like the other case
because in this case you started with two halves, remember, the point
before he said was different was you started with two wholes, right,
whichever one the whole being significant, but you started with two wholes.
Here you started with two halves so he says presumably that means
it remains a שני sheini even if you go ahead and add
the final half, which is exactly analogous ignoring all the differences between
טומאה ומחשבה. tuma umachshava. Anyway, מאי לאו אף על גב דהדר מליה
mai lav af al gav dehadar malyei even when you went afterwards
and filled it up, gave the other half of the ראשון, rishon,
so the גמרא Gemara says לא דילמא דלא הדר מליה lo dilma
delo hadar malyei no maybe it only means until at this stage
it operates as a שני, sheini, if you were to add the
other half maybe it would go back and operate as a ראשון.
rishon. Okay, כי אתא רב דימי, ki ata Rav Dimi, so that's
their debate. כי אתא רב דימי אמר חצי זית חוץ למקומו וחצי
זית חוץ לזמנו וחצי זית חוץ לזמנו. ki ata Rav Dimi amar
chatzi zayis chutz limkomo vechatzi zayis chutz lizmano vechatzi zayis chutz lizmano.
Now,
for רב דימי Rav Dimi he says this is obvious that this
is פסול, pasul, when you hit the first זית zayis it was
פסול pasul it doesn't become כשר kosher again. רב דימי Rav Dimi
says I'm going to tell you even a more interesting case that
is פסול pasul and and not פיגול. pigul. Meaning like it becomes
not פסול? pasul?
No, no I thought it was not פסול pasul not פיגול. pigul.
Right, right, right, פסול pasul it means specifically not פיגול. pigul. So
רב דימי Rav Dimi says his case was what was his case?
חצי זית חוץ למקומו chatzi zayis chutz limkomo if you did half,
okay, you know what I'm just going to write מקום makom I'm
going we know it's a half, so it's not interesting to write
a half of it. מקום, makom, זמן,
זמן. zman zman Okay,
each one of these is a half, we'll write the half above.
Okay, so he said in this case logically you would be much
more inclined to say פיגול, pigul, right, because the two זמנים zmanim
come side by side. So you could have said this was a
half he didn't think he said he thought a half חוץ למקומו,
chutz limkomo, another half חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, another half חוץ לזמנו.
chutz lizmano. So you might say combine these two and say if
he had said a half חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo and a full
one חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano obviously that would be פיגול pigul a
half thought does not is not an עירוב מחשבות. eruv machshavos. But
here he says because you have half, half, half, by the time
you got here you already thought about a full כזית kezayis and
it was פסול pasul and not פיגול, pigul, okay. So this case
he says is obviously פסול pasul but in and not פיגול. pigul.
This case is obviously not פיגול pigul but even this case is
not פיגול pigul because by the time you got to the first
כזית kezayis you were at a
you were at a full כזית kezayis that was not פיגול. pigul.
Okay, כי אתא רב דימי. ki ata Rav Dimi. So בר קפרא
Bar Kappara actually said that case is פיגול, pigul, but the implication
being I keep on jumping ahead to the next line in the
גמרא. Gemara. בר קפרא Bar Kappara says this is פיגול pigul because
you do have a full כזית kezayis next to each other, so
בר קפרא Bar Kappara says, excuse me, בר קפרא Bar Kappara says
this case is not because obviously it intervened, that that חוץ למקומו
chutz limkomo intervened. But here where you actually have a full כזית
kezayis together, that is actually going to be פיגול. pigul. This is
clearly not פיגול, pigul, this will be פיגול. pigul. That's what בר
קפרא Bar Kappara says, okay. אין
חצי כזית מועיל במקום כזית. Ein chatzi kezayis mo'il b'makom kezayis. כי
אתא רבין אמר, Ki asa Ravin amar, and now when רבין Ravin
came he said, חצי כזית חוץ לזמנו וחצי כזית חוץ לזמנו וחצי
כזית חוץ למקומו. chatzi kezayis chutz lizmano v'chatzi kezayis chutz lizmano v'chatzi
kezayis chutz limkomo. No, no, no, in this case he said like
this: he said חצי כזית חוץ לזמנו, chatzi kezayis chutz lizmano, חצי
כזית... chatzi kezayis...
it should surely be פיגול pigul then. What?
He said זמן זמן מקום. zman zman makom. Yeah, right,
so there, right, זמן zman, זמן zman. and מקום, makom, that should
surely be פיגול pigul because here by the time you get to
the first כזית, kezayis, right, you have פיגול pigul and a half
of a כזית kezayis of a half of a כזית kezayis מקום
makom is not a thought to be מבטל. mevatel. You have פיגול
pigul and then you thought about a half of a כזית kezayis
of מקום. makom. So בר קפרא, Bar Kappara, only that, only this
is פיגול pigul because before, at the moment of the first כזית,
kezayis, you're already at פיגול. pigul. But this is not because and
even this is not. Even though these are next to each other,
since at the moment of the first כזית kezayis it's פסול, posul,
this doesn't become פיגול, pigul, this doesn't become פיגול, pigul, only this
becomes פיגול. pigul. Okay? כי אתא רבין אמר, Ki asa Ravin amar,
חצי כזית חוץ לזמנו וחצי כזית חוץ לזמנו וחצי כזית חוץ למקומו.
chatzi kezayis chutz lizmano v'chatzi kezayis chutz lizmano v'chatzi kezayis chutz limkomo.
That case, תני בר קפרא פיגול. tani Bar Kappara pigul. אין חצי
כזית מועיל במקום כזית. Ein chatzi kezayis mo'il b'makom kezayis. Okay? So
you have three options that you could say any of these are
פיגול. pigul. This one clearly is פיגול, pigul, okay, because this one
by the time you get to the first כזית kezayis it's already
פיגול. pigul. Okay, but these you could debate it. רבא Rava says
this is not פיגול, pigul, anyway, so we have different opinions. Here
you could say that this isn't, I'm sorry, רב Rav says even
this is פיגול. pigul. It wakes up, but the more obvious thing
to say is that it's not because at the first כזית kezayis
it's not, okay, פיגול. pigul. And this is interesting. On the one
hand at the first כזית kezayis it's not. On the other hand
you have the two half of the זמנים zmans next to each
other. Okay?
So this is clearly, this is the one thing that is clearly
פיגול pigul and if בר קפרא Bar Kappara says that this is
פיגול pigul presumably he's saying none of these are פיגול. pigul. But
רב Rav says even that up there is פיגול. pigul. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
רב
אשי מתני הכי,
Rav Ashi
masni hachi, חצי כזית חוץ לזמנו וכזית... chatzi kezayis chutz lizmano u'kezayis...
Now רב אשי Rav Ashi says here's what you think. A חצי
כזית חוץ לזמנו chatzi kezayis chutz lizmano and then you think, oh
and the next כזית kezayis I'm going to do, I'm going to
do
חציו חוץ למקומו וחציו חוץ לזמנו. chetzyo chutz limkomo v'chetzyo chutz lizmano.
Okay? So you think is, okay, so your thought is, what's your
thought? You say a half
חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, זמן, zman, and then the next one you
say I'm going to split it, half of it will be חוץ
לזמנו chutz lizmano and half will be חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo.
But first he said חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo.
Oh, did I get it wrong? He said למקומו limkomo first?
No, no, no, but then he said the next one.
Oh, it doesn't matter, we're not dealing with תפס לשון ראשון, tofas
lashon rishon, okay? The point is that you've combined them. Okay, so
now in this case, okay, what would you say, right? Would you
say that in this... so let's take a look. So in this
case, חצי כזית חוץ לזמנו וכזית חציו חוץ למקומו וחציו
חוץ לזמנו, chatzi kezayis chutz lizmano u'kezayis chetzyo chutz limkomo v'chetzyo chutz
lizmano, תני בר קפרא פיגול. tani Bar Kappara pigul. אין חצי כזית
מועיל במקום כזית. Ein chatzi kezayis mo'il b'makom kezayis. In this case
it's פיגול pigul because in this case, right, you get
when you pull in the other thought here of this of this
other כזית, kezayis, okay, you only have of a half of a
כזית kezayis of מקום makom present. The half of a כזית kezayis
מקום makom cannot combine, you know, in this case it sounds like
he's saying that in this case actually, surprisingly, this would not be
פיגול pigul because in this case I could draw the line here
and have a כזית kezayis of something other than פיגול. pigul. Okay?
So this case, because I could draw the line here, even though
it would not be sequential in time, this is פסול posul and
not פיגול. pigul. But in this case I can't draw the line
anywhere and get something, right, because as soon as I had this
thought
to combine it with this thought, I'm immediately going to get a
full כזית kezayis of חוץ לזמנו.
chutz lizmano. Doesn't matter which he had in the full one there,
doesn't matter which thought came first?
That's what I was asking him, you're saying no.
No, I mean we could switch it, I don't think it does.
I think his whole point was
well then you're saying it's just a bigger חידוש chiddush because he
even said that case. Right, right, but his point is it doesn't
matter what order he said it, this is seen as a half-half
thing. It's just seen as a half-half because he said a כזית
kezayis half this way half that way. So therefore, since it's seen
as a whole thing, when you combine it with that, there's no
way you can combine that and get פסול pasul without being פיגול
pigul because at the moment of combining you have a full כזית
kzayis of זמן. zman. So here, he says this will be פיגול
kzayis of זמן zman and only half כזית kzayis of מקום. makom.
Whereas this, even though if you do it sequentially, you have פיגול,
pigul, since you could stop here and combine it that way, it
sounds like he would say that that's פסול pasul and not פיגול,
pigul, which is a big חידוש. chiddush. Okay. All right. תני בר
קפרא אין חצי
זית מהו במקום כזית. Tani Ber Koppera ein khatzi zayis mo b’makom
kzayis. Okay, so we are now done with all those half כזיתים.
kzeisim. Okay, I hope you enjoyed that.
Let me just check
רש״י Rashi to make sure I read this right.
רש״י Rashi says different than I did. Hold on.
I think, hold on. Wait, wait, wait, hold on. Let me get
this straight.
No, I'm sorry. רש״י Rashi says the opposite I did, I apologize.
Okay, maybe somebody else says what I said, I don't know. But
okay, just let me just quickly correct this and then we're going
to move on. What I said was, was that he was working
in this progression and that he was going to say
none of this is פיגול pigul
because you could recombine it, and the only thing that's פיגול pigul
is this because it forces you to sort of have it all
at the same time. That's the way I was saying it. רש״י
Rashi says the exact opposite. רש״י Rashi actually says that he would
say all of this is פיגול, pigul, okay?
Even רבא's Rava case is פיגול pigul or whatever, any way in
which you combine it. The only thing is I might have thought
this wasn't פיגול. pigul. The reason I might have thought this wasn't
פיגול pigul was because this כזית, kzayis, רש״י's Rashi way I'm sure
makes more sense, because this כזית kzayis here is already a full
פסול pasul כזית, kzayis, right? It's half and half, it's already combined,
it's a full פסול pasul כזית. kzayis. So I might have said,
this is a thought of a half of זמנו, zmano, and this
is a full כזית kzayis of פסול. psul. You understand? If I
just zoom out, this is a full כזית kzayis of פסול. psul.
So since this is a full כזית kzayis of פסול, psul, I
might have thought that okay, it's פסול, pasul, it's not פיגול. pigul.
You have a full כזית kzayis of פסול psul and a half
כזית kzayis of פיגול. pigul. Okay, and the חידוש chiddush is, no,
even in this, the two זמנים zmanim will combine. The way רש״י
Rashi says it is, it's like רבא Rava here, that the two
זמנים zmanim combine even with this in the middle, but it's a
bigger חידוש chiddush than רבא, Rava, because here in רבא Rava the
half כזית kzayis of מקום makom was independent, here where it's all
wrapped together, you might think that this is a full כזית kzayis
of פסול psul and therefore the thing remains פסול pasul and not
פיגול, pigul, and his חידוש chiddush is that you're able to sort
of detach it and recombine it. Okay, so my apologies. The way
רש״י Rashi understood it, okay, this was saying not that this is
everything, not that everything else is פסול, pasul, the opposite, everything is
פיגול pigul and even this is פיגול, pigul, even though you have
a full combined כזית kzayis there. All right. Fine. Let's move on.
Okay, so you have all those different opinions about at which stage
does the half כזית kzayis interrupt. רבא Rava says the half כזית
kzayis doesn't interrupt here, you step back and you wrap it up.
And according to רב אשי Rav Ashi the way רש״י Rashi is
reading it, it doesn't, the half כזית kzayis doesn't interrupt even here,
even though it's all mixed together in this כזית. kzayis. Okay, and
others say that you know, the half כזית kzayis can interrupt maybe
even in more places, maybe even if the half כזית kzayis came
before, like it can interrupt even not between. But presumably this case
everybody would agree is פיגול pigul because this case sequentially, once you
get to a half and a half and you're at a full
כזית kzayis you have חוץ לזמנו, khutz lizmano, everybody would agree that
that case is פיגול. pigul. Fine. Time to move on. אמר רב
אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, says רב אשי. Rav Ashi. אמר רב אשי,
Amar Rav Ashi,
where were we? אמר רב ינאי, Amar Rav Yanai,
excuse me. חישב שיאכלוהו כלבים למחר, Chishiv sheyokhlu hu klavim l’makhar,
פיגול. pigul. Let's say your planning was not that you would eat
it tomorrow, but you'd feed it to your dogs tomorrow. Okay, is
that considered a thought of eating it at the wrong time? So
he says yes, eating of dogs is considered eating. דכתיב ואת איזבל
יאכלו הכלבים בחלק יזרעאל. d’khsiv v’es izevel yokhlu haklavim b’khelek yizreel. איזבל
Izevel will be consumed by the dogs. Now, of course we consider
the eating of dogs eating, you know, what's the חידוש? chiddush? Like
there's, תוספות Tosfos says there's many פסוקים psukim that speak about dogs
eating and so on. Okay, so תוספות Tosfos says you know, what
like just we read by בהר, Behar, תהיה כל תבואתה לאכול, tihyeh
kol tvuatah le’ekhol, you know, it talks about the animals eating the
grain or whatever. So תוספות Tosfos says no, the חידוש chiddush is
that even when they eat something... that is,
meat. Now of course I don't understand, dogs are carnivores, of course
they eat meat. So I don't exactly get what תוספות—anyway, Tosafos but
תוספות Tosafos raises the question don't we always know that the תורה
Torah refers to eating of animals as eating. The bigger חידוש chiddush
is not just which isn't answered by this פסוק pasuk is not
just that the word יאכלו, yochlu, the verb, is used by it,
but that you would think that the whole point is redirecting the
human eating that would be done from, at the right time to
doing it at the wrong time. Just because something else has a
label of eating, if it's not the normal thing that should have
properly been done to this meat, you would not think that that
would be a relevant פיגול piggul thought. Right, you would just think
that you're just planning to destroy it. The פיגול piggul thought is
you're doing the natural, the normal thing that should be done, but
you're doing it at the wrong time. Anyway, somehow he quotes the
פסוק pasuk and decides that that's considered a פיגול piggul thought. אלא
מעתה ella me'ata says the גמרא, Gemara, מתקיף לה רב אמי—Rav maskif
lah Rav Ami Ami challenged this. אלא מעתה ella me'ata if that's
true, חישב שתאכלו אש למחר, chishev shetochlu esh lemachar, דכתיב dichsiv תאכלו
אש לא נופח. tochlu esh lo nopach. So, not,
a fire that wouldn't even, that wasn't even like billowed or whatever
will consume it anyway. So we use the word eating by fire.
So if you plan to burn it tomorrow, you think that'll be
פיגול? piggul?
הכי נמי—הכי נמי דפיגול? Should I say it's פיגול? piggul? וכי תימא,
vechi teima, הכי נמי, hacha nami yes. והתנן: vehatnan: לאכול כחצי זית
ולהקטיר כחצי זית כשר, leechol kechatzi zayis ulehaktir kechatzi zayis kasher, שאין
אכילה והקטרה מצטרפין. she'ein achilah vehaktarah mitztarpin. If I plan to eat
a half a כזית kezayis and to burn a half a כזית
kezayis on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, that's not a צירוף. tzeruf. It's a
צירוף tzeruf right when I do like a half of a כזית
kezayis tomorrow and a half a כזית, kezayis, in the wrong place.
But two different types of acts, eating a half a כזית kezayis
and burning a half a כזית kezayis on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, don't
combine. Now he says, if burning something is considered אכילה, achilah, so
why don't I say that it combines? It's אכילה achilah and
אכילה. achilah. So
the גמרא's Gemara's answer is, you know what, actually it would combine.
אי דאפקי בלשון אכילה הכי נמי. ei de'afkei belashon achilah hacha nami.
If basically you said, I'm going to have it consumed by the
fire, not I'm going to offer it up, I'm going to be
מקטיר maktir it. If you said I'm going to eat a half
of a כזית kezayis tomorrow and be מאכיל ma'achil a half of
a כזית kezayis to the מזבח mizbe'ach tomorrow, and you use the
verb אכילה, achilah, maybe it would
combine. הכא במאי עסקינן דאפקי בלשון הקטרה דלשון אכילה לחוד ולשון הקטרה
לחוד. hacha bemai askinan de'afkei belashon haktarah delashon achilah lachud velashon haktarah
lachud. Which is very bizarre,
because the whole thing is bizarre. It's bizarre that the whole point
of פיגול piggul is you take the act that you should have
done or that should have been done in the מזבח mizbe'ach and
it's done in the wrong time and the wrong place. Not that
we're talking about a totally separate act. And just because you can
give it the same label, nobody would have been said I would
have fulfilled my obligation of eating the meat just because you could
give it the label of אכילה achilah if I fed it to
my dogs. So since that wouldn't satisfy my obligation, why should that
constitute פיגול? piggul? Okay, and it's also bizarre that the גמרא Gemara
actually says it just depends on exactly how you frame in your
mind your plan. If basically say I'm going to burn it, then
it's not פיגול. piggul. If you say I'm going to feed it
to the fire, then it is פיגול. piggul. Very, very strange. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara continues. Yes.
What if the thought was I'm going to feed it to my
dogs in the right time? Is there just something
פסול pasul
about—well, obviously then that would not invalidate the קרבן. korban. And if
you actually did that, you would, it'd be a mistreatment of הקדש.
hekdesh. It might be מעילה, me'ilah, whatever, well it depends. But anyway,
but it would not invalidate the קרבן. korban. Right. If you said
basically I'm not going to eat it, I'm going to burn it,
I'm going to whatever, all those things are bad, are like improper
thoughts, but they're not the types of thoughts that invalidate. Okay, so
now by the way just to show you how bizarre this is,
תוספות Tosafos says, חישב שיאכלו כלבים למחר פיגול, chishev sheyochlu klavim lemachar
piggul, תוספות Tosafos says בסוף כל הפסולין אמרינן דחישב שיאכלו טמאים לא
הוי פיגול. besof kol hapsulin amrinan dechishev sheyochlu tme'im lo havei piggul.
If I plan to feed it to טמא tamei people, it's not
פיגול piggul because טמא tamei people shouldn't be eating it. וצריך לפרש
טעם מאי גרע אכילת כלבים? v'tzarich lefareish ta'am mai gara achilas klavim?
Feeding to my dogs, since it uses the word feeding, that is
פיגול. piggul. Feeding to somebody who's טמא, tamei, that's not פיגול. piggul.
You know what I'm saying? It's like bizarre, right? Clearly from that
later גמרא, Gemara, it's clear that פיגול piggul is a type of
eating that otherwise would be okay but it's the wrong time. So
if the person is טמא, tamei, that doesn't make פיגול. piggul. So
of course dogs shouldn't make פיגול. piggul. Very strange. Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. בעי רב אשי: ba'ei Rav Ashi:
רב אשי Rav Ashi asks the following. חישב לאכול כזית בשני בני
אדם מהו? chishev leechol kezayis bishnei bnei adam mahu? I'm going to
have this כזית kezayis tomorrow and I'll split it with my wife,
okay, or I'll give it to my two friends and they'll each
eat a half of a
כזית. kezayis. מהו, mahu, what do we say? בתר מחשבה אזלינן דאיכא
שיעורא? basar machshava azlinan de'ika shiura? Since my plan was a full
כזית, kezayis, therefore it becomes פיגול. piggul. I'm planning to have a
full כזית kezayis consumed tomorrow. או בתר אוכלין אזלינן וליכא שיעורא? o
basar ochlin azlinan veleika shiura? Or do we say each act of
eating is a half of a כזית kezayis act of eating and
each one is distinct? And there's not a שיעור. shiur. Okay, now
the whole fact that we combine a half כזית kezayis and a
half כזית kezayis should make you feel that even if you went
by אכילה, achila, why not combine? But anyway, that's the question. Okay,
so אמר אביי תא שמע, Amar Abaye ta shema, which is basically
what Abaye says. לאכול כחצי זית ולהקטיר כחצי זית כשר. le'echol k'chatzi
zayis u'lehaktir k'chatzi zayis kasher. If it's to eat a half כזית
kezayis and to have the altar burn a half כזית, kezayis, then
that doesn't combine. שאין אכילה והקטרה מצטרפין. she'ein achila v'haktara mitztarpin. Those
are two separate acts, eating and being burnt on the altar. Abaye
makes a very cogent argument.
Says Abaye, הא לאכול ולאכול—so ha le'echol v'le'echol the altar's eating is
a different thing than eating the meat. And the only reason it
doesn't combine is because it's not considered eating. It's considered like, you
know, burning on the altar. So if it was an eating and
an eating, דומיא דלאכול ולהקטיר, dumya d'le'echol v'lehaktir, parallel to me eating
and the altar eating—so instead of me and the altar, it was
me and, you know, and my friend, you know, Elliot or
something—so Elliot as opposed to altar. Anyway, so you know, so in
that case, והיכי דמי בשני בני אדם, v'heichi dami b'shnei bnei adam,
מצטרף, mitztaref, that would combine. It doesn't matter it's two separate, you
know, things doing the eating, as long as they're two humans and
not a human and an altar. שמע מינה, shma mina, that actually
is a pretty explicit proof. Okay, בעי רבא. Ba'ei Rava. Here's Rava's
question. חישב לאכול כזית ביתר מכדי אכילת פרס, Chishev le'echol kezayis b'yaser
m'kdei achilas pras, מהו? mahu? I'm going to eat a כזית kezayis
tomorrow, but I'm going to take my sweet time doing it. And
I'm going to eat it a little, little bit at a time
and it's going to take me a half hour to eat the
whole כזית. kezayis. More than the normal amount of time that you
combine eatings. You combine eatings כדי אכילת פרס. kdei achilas pras. What
is that? Five minutes or something like that. That's when it's considered
one act of eating, whether it's for a מצוה, mitzvah, a little
bit of a מצה matzah now, a little later, a little later—was
I יוצא yotzei my מצוה? mitzvah? Did you eat it within אכילת
פרס? achilas pras? פרס Pras is a half a loaf of bread,
so which is whatever we call it, five minutes or something, ten
minutes. Okay, then I was יוצא yotzei the מצוה, mitzvah, otherwise I
wasn't. And we have it for forbidden acts—eating חלב, cheilev, חמץ, chametz,
you know. If it's within that amount of time, I transgress. Here,
does it need to be the thought to eat it within that
amount of time?
ביתר מכדי אכילת פרס מהו? b'yaser m'kdei achilas pras mahu? לאכילת גבוה
מדמינן לה? l'achilas gavoah madminan lah? Do we say, well, when it
burns on the altar, it takes more than that amount of time
for it to
burn? או לאכילת הדיוט מדמינן לה? o l'achilas hedyot madminan lah? Or
do we compare it to your natural eating you would do? And
that would be defined as within אכילת פרס. achilas pras. It would
seem that it should depend. If you're planning on you eating it,
it would have to be a plan to do it within כדי
אכילת פרס. kdei achilas pras. If you're planning for the altar to
consume it, it wouldn't, right? It might—logically you would think it depends
on what your plan is. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר אביי
תא שמע, Amar Abaye ta shema, come and
hear, לאכול כחצי זית ולהקטיר כחצי זית כשר, le'echol k'chatzi zayis u'lehaktir
k'chatzi zayis kasher, שאין אכילה והקטרה מצטרפין. she'ein achila v'haktara mitztarpin. Back
to this: half a כזית kezayis of me and half a כזית
kezayis for the altar, it—because we're
two—because human eating and altar eating don't combine. טעמא דלאכול ולהקטיר. Ta'ama
d'le'echol v'lehaktir. The reason is because it's human and altar. הא לאכול
ולאכול מצטרף. Ha le'echol v'le'echol mitztaref. But if it was instead of
the altar eating the other half, a human being eating the other
half, but he was eating it like an altar eats it, which
means taking his sweet old time—presumably it would still presumably combine. והקטר
ביתר מכדי אכילת פרס הוא. v'haktar b'yaser m'kdei achilas pras hu. So
but that's going to take this guy more than אכילת פרס—like achilas
pras when an altar does it, it's going to be more than
אכילת פרס. achilas pras. So you see, if it weren't for the
fact that it was an altar, just because it's taking—it's going to
happen over a period of time—is not a basis for saying that
it should not be a good thought. So the גמרא Gemara says,
no, דילמא בהסק גדול. dilma b'hesek gadol. You don't know. Maybe even
when the plan was about the—maybe—meaning maybe the idea that in a
parallel case by a human, maybe we're thinking about a case where
an altar would consume it very quickly. You had a big fire
and the altar did consume it within a few minutes. Okay, and
therefore in a parallel case by a human, it would combine. So
you don't really have an answer, but logically you would think that
if your thought is about burning it on an altar, it should
not be proscribed by, you know, limited by the amount of time
you're planning on it taking, because that's natural for the altar. If
your plan is on human consumption,
presumably you should think it should go by the amount of normal
time you define eating for human consumption. But the גמרא Gemara leaves
that as an open question, for some reason maybe here we would
borrow from the reality by the altar and say that you actually
have more time. You know, your plan could be for something taking
more time.
Okay, לאכול כחצי זית ולהקטיר כחצי זית כשר. le'echol k'chatzi zayis u'lehaktir
k'chatzi zayis kasher. So says the גמרא, Gemara, now back—this is the
one we've been referencing, now we're going to focus on it. Half
a כזית kezayis eating, half a כזית kezayis burning on the altar,
does not combine. טעמא דלאכול ולהקטיר. Ta'ama d'le'echol v'lehaktir. הא לאכול ולאכול
דבר שאין דרכו לאכול מצטרף. Ha le'echol v'le'echol davar she'ein darko le'echol
mitztaref. גמרא Gemara says one minute, what are you planning on burning
on the altar when it doesn't combine? What do you burn on
the altar? The entrails, right? So it says, if I plan on
me eating half a כזית kezayis of meat and the altar consuming
half of a כזית kezayis of entrails, then it's כשר. kasher. Right?
Which suggests that if it was going to be me eating a
half of a כזית kezayis of entrails plus a half of a
כזית kezayis of meat, it would combine. But if you remember, that
was the question we had way at the beginning: does a plan
of me eating the stuff that should—that's normally eaten by the altar—is
that considered a thought about אכילה? achila? You got it? Okay,
because... Right,
here's your altar. Whatever. Okay.
And here's and here's me
or here's somebody. Okay, I don't know. All right, anyway, whatever. Okay,
so now, if he this is
going I'm going to eat a half of this, and that's food,
and my thought is also to put a half of the כזית
kezayit on the altar, and that is this is food and this
is
אימורין. emurim. So it says that those two halves don't combine because
it's eating and the burning on the altar. Okay? But it sounds
like if I was going to plan for me to eat that
half of a כזית, kezayit, right, it would combine even though this
is stuff that's normally not eaten by me, even though it's stuff
that's normally burned on the altar. Okay, and that was an issue
that we discussed, whether that type of a thought for me to
eat the stuff that's on the altar does make פיגול pigul or
not. So let's take a look at that. טעמא דאכילה ולהקטיר הא
אכילה ואכילה דבר שאין דרכו הא אכילה ואכילה דבר שאין דרכו לאכול
מצטרף. taima de-achila u-lehaktir ha achila ve-achila davar she-ein darko ha achila
ve-achila davar she-ein darko le-achol mitztaref.
Hakta- sounds like if I was going to eat plan to eat
that half of a כזית kezayit of אימורין, emurim, it would combine.
הכא תני רישא לאכול את שדרכו לאכול את שדרכו לאכול אין את
שאין דרכו לא. haka tani reisha le-achol et she-darko le-achol et she-darko
le-achol in at she-ein darko lo. Remember
the earlier משנה mishna said, I'm only חייב chayiv if I plan
on eating the meat, not if I plan on eating the stuff
that goes on the altar. אמר רבי ירמיה הא מני רבי אליעזר
היא, amar Rabbi Yirmeya ha meni Rabbi Eliezer hi, you should remember
this from earlier. Fine, but this last point that suggest that implies
that that would combine follows רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, דאמר מחשבין מאכילת
אדם לאכילת מזבח ומאכילת מזבח לאכילת אדם, de-amar mechashvin me-achilat adam le-achilat
mizbe'ach u-me-achilat mizbe'ach le-achilat adam,
if I plan to burn the meat on the altar then or
if I plan to eat the entrails, even as long as it's
you know that that still would work for פיגול. pigul. Even though
it is not the stuff I normally eat or not the stuff
the altar normally eats, since it's the stuff of the קרבן korban
that is eaten, okay, then any any form of me eating it
or the altar eating it would be would be פיגול. pigul. That's
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. דתנן השוחט את הזבח, de-tenan ha-shochet et ha-zevach,
the משנה mishna will say, which we'll get to, you slaughter the
sacrifice, לאכול דבר שאין דרכו לאכול להקטיר דבר שאין דרכו להקטיר כשר.
le-achol davar she-ein darko le-achol le-haktir davar she-ein darko le-haktir kasher. If
you plan on eating stuff that's normally not eaten by humans, I
mean it could be not eaten because it's the hooves, or could
be not eaten because it's the entrails, or you plan on burning
the stuff that's not normally burned, it's כשר. kasher. Okay, הא אין
מחשבין מאכילת מזבח לאכילת אדם. ha ein mechashvin me-achilat mizbe'ach le-achilat adam.
רבי
אליעזר פוסל Rabbi Eliezer posel and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no,
that does invalidate it. Okay. אביי אמר, Abaye amar, אביי Abaye says,
אפילו תימא רבנן, afilu tema Rabbanan, even the Rabbis, ולא תימא הא
אכילה ואכילה דבר שאין דרכו לאכול אלא לימא הא אכילה ואכילה דבר
שדרכו לאכול. ve-lo tema ha achila ve-achila davar she-ein darko le-achol ela
lema ha achila ve-achila davar she-darko le-achol.
Meaning, you got it wrong. אביי Abaye says, the גמרא Gemara says
this and this don't combine. It's not suggesting that if I were
to plan to eat that half כזית kezayit that goes on the
altar it would combine. Here, this is natural, my eating this, and
this is natural, it burning the אימורין. emurim. Even though these are
two natural things, because they're different acts, they don't combine. That doesn't
mean that if I were to plan to eat this it would
combine. It means if I were to plan to eat another half
of a כזית kezayit which would be natural for me to do
it would combine, right?
That's a bad inference. Just because I said this is something that
by if you had a full כזית kezayit would be a problem,
this is something if you had a full כזית kezayit would be
a problem, you take a half and a half, it doesn't make
a problem. That's what the משנה mishna is saying. It doesn't mean
that if I plan to eat that half it would be a
problem. It means if I plan to do two halves that were
both in my world it would be a problem, okay? הא אכילה
ואכילה דבר שאין אלא לימא הא אכילה ואכילה דבר שדרכו לאכול מאי
קמשמע לן?
ha achila ve-achila davar she-ein
ela lema ha achila ve-achila davar she-darko le-achol mai kamashma lan?
So what's the חידוש? chiddush? אי דבר שדרכו לאכול קמשמע לן, i
davar she-darko le-achol kamashma lan, if it's to tell you, you know,
that it's what you combine two halves, מרישא שמע מינה כחצי זית
בחוץ וכחצי זית למחר פסול. me-reisha shma mina ki chatzi zayit ba-chutz
ve-chatzi zayit le-machar pasul. Okay so we already know. אי אכילה ולהקטיר
מדיוקא דרישא שמע מינה. i achila u-lehaktir miduyka de-reisha shma mina. If
it's telling me, no, it's not telling me any implication. It's telling
me what it says it's telling me. You don't combine eating and
burning. Don't try to infer from that oh, if I were to
eat this half it would combine. It's not telling you to infer
anything. Just pay attention to what it is saying. Eating and burning
don't combine. So the גמרא Gemara says, I didn't need it to
tell me that. I could have inferred it. How could I have
inferred it? מדיוקא דרישא שמע מינה. miduyka de-reisha shma mina.
Why? Because the רישא reisha says, לאכול דבר שדרכו לאכול אין שאין
דרכו לאכול לא. le-achol davar she-darko le-achol in she-ein darko le-achol lo.
So if I plan I'm only חייב chayiv if I plan on
eating things that I normally eat. If I were to plan on
eating אימורין, emurim, I would not be it wouldn't be פיגול. pigul.
השתא ומה אכילה ואכילה דבר שאין דרכו לאכול לא מצטרף, hashta u-ma
achila ve-achila davar she-ein darko le-achol lo mitztaref, if I plan on
eating אימורין, emurim, it doesn't combine, אכילה ולהקטיר מיבעיא? achila u-lehaktir miba?
How much more so if I plan on feeding those אימורין emurim
to the altar it doesn't combine, which is a bizarre argument. Okay,
which is what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. Meaning, the גמרא's
Gemara going to say like this: why did I need the משנה
mishna to tell me my eating and the altar doesn't combine, if
I already know that when I try to eat
this plus a half of the כזית kezayis of אימורים, imurim, okay,
if I already know that that doesn't combine,
even if I'm planning on doing the full eating of it, it
doesn't combine because it's אימורים. imurim. How much more so would it
not combine if it's being offered on the altar. Now that's a
really bad קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, because the reason this doesn't combine
is because this is not natural for me to eat. But maybe
this plus this does combine. This is natural for me to eat
and that's natural for the altar to eat. Okay, so the גמרא's
Gemara saying you could not have figured out that this doesn't combine
just because these don't combine when I'm planning on eating them, okay,
which is what it says. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says: No.
לאכול ולהקטיר איצטריכא. le'echol u'lehaktir itzricha. No, you need it to tell
me that doesn't combine. סלקא דעתך אמינא התם הוא דלאו כארחיה קמחשב.
Salka da'atach amina hasam hu d'lav k'orchei kamachshev. Here it doesn't combine
because it's not natural for me to eat this.
אבל הכא דבהאי כארחיה ובהאי כארחיה. Aval hacha d'behai k'orchei u'behai k'orchei.
It's natural for me to eat that and it's natural for the
altar to eat that.
אימא ליצטריף קא משמע לן Eima litztaref kamashma llan that they don't.
Okay, so that was very complicated to get to I think what
we would have sort of intuitively understood to begin with. הדרן עלך
כל הזבחים שקבלו דמם. Hadrach alach kol hazvachim shekiblu damam. Shapi... very
good. We've now finished the second פרק perek and at least you
think we're out of פיגול, pigul, but we're never really out of
פיגול. pigul. The next one actually gets to a whole discussion about
פסולים, psulim, but it's going to be relevant to פיגול pigul as
well. So let's start the next פרק. perek. כל הפסולים ששחטו שחיטתן
כשרה. Kol hapsulim sheshachtu shchitatam ksheira. So anybody who is normally invalid
to serve as a כהן, kohen, he's טמא, tamei, he's an אונן,
onen, he's standing not standing on the floor,
it's a non-כהן, kohen, etc. All these people since if they שחטו
shachtu for שחיטה shechita they're kosher. שהשחיטה כשרה בזרים, Shehashechita ksheira b'zarim,
because שחיטה shechita can be done by non-כהנים, kohanim, ובנשים, u'vnashim, women.
So here's very important: women not only can they be שוחטים shochtim
for, you know, חולין, chullin, women can even be שוחטות shochtot for
the קרבנות, korbanot, okay, ובנשים ובעבדים ובטמאים. u'vnashim u'vavadim u'vtmeyim. ואפילו בקדשי
קדשים. Ve'afilu bekodshel kodashim. They can even do it in the Holy
of Holies. Now the Holy of Holies meaning basically anything that's not
a שלמים, shelamim, okay, like an עולה, olah, a חטאת, chatat, or
whatever is stuff that has to be slaughtered, okay, right
again to remind you of the basic look of the place, right?
I mean whatever. Here was the עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim, there was
the עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, there
was
the altar.
Okay, fine. So this is the... this
line is the עזרה. Azara. That's where the real קדושת עזרה Kedushat
Azara stands. So if you're a טמא tamei person you could stand
over here and the קרבן korban could be here and you could
שחט shcht by staying outside of the עזרה. Azara. Okay. But קדשי
קדשים Kodshei Kodashim had to be slaughtered over here. All right. So
קדשי... right, sort of like deep in there. All right. So it's
telling you, so you might think that maybe it's one thing to
שחט shecht. קדשים קלים, Kodshim Kalim, maybe קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim these
טמא tamei peop... these invalid people can't slaughter it. And the answer
is that even though these are holier sacrifices and have to be
more inner and by the side of the altar, if you get
a really long knife, okay, or whatever תוספות Tosafot says maybe you're
coming into it from that side or something. Anyway, as long as
you can do it without going into the עזרה Azara if you're
a type of person that can't go into the עזרה, Azara, right?
Women can go into the עזרה, Azara, but a טמא tamei person
can't or whatever. Anyway, all right, so even קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim
it would be kosher. ובלבד שלא יהיו טמאים נוגעים בבשר. Ubivad shelo
yehu tmeim nogim babasar.
Just don't, if you're טמא, tamei, don't touch the meat, don't be
מטמא mtamei the meat. Okay. So have a really long knife, have
it be something that's not מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, whatever the case
might be. Okay now, because all of these people are kosher to
do the שחיטה, shechita, לפיכך הן פוסלין במחשבה. lefikach hein poslim bemachshava.
Therefore
because their thoughts would invalidate the קרבן korban if they were thinking
פיגול pigul thoughts. It's not a הלכה halacha that פיגול pigul can
only be thought of by the כהנים. kohanim. The הלכה halacha is
by the way though that again this goes back to what I
was saying on שבת Shabbos about you know the whole fact that
we've move it away from the owners and focus on the כהנים,
kohanim, פיגול pigul thought of the owners is irrelevant, okay. There actually
is I think one שיטה shita that it is but whatever, פיגול
pigul thought of the owners is irrelevant. פיגול pigul thought is only
relevant by the people doing the עבודה. avoda. But
by שחיטה shechita that's not limited to כהנים. kohanim. All these people
because their שחיטה's shechita kosher, if they are doing the שחיטה shechita
their פיגול pigul thought is meaningful. Now before we get onto the
second part of the משנה mishna I just want to pause for
a moment to read this תוספות Tosafot שהשחיטה כשרה בנשים. shehashechita ksheira
bnashim.
Let's take a look at this תוספות. Tosafot. He says: הגמרא מוכח
דנשים שוחטות אפילו לכתחילה. hagemara muvchach denashim shochtot afilu lechatchila. Okay
that even women even לכתחילה lechatchila can be שוחט. shochet. דתנן ששחטו
דיעבד משום דבעי למתני טמאים. Dehatnan sheshachtu b'di'avad mishum deba'ei l'mitnei tmeim.
The only language of "if they slaughtered it's good" refers to the
טמא tamei people. דלכתחילה לא D'lechatchila lo to... but they shouldn't because
of a concern they might get the meat טמא. tamei. Let's take
a look at this תוספות. Tosfos. He says the גמרא Gemara מוכח
muchach דנשים denashim שוחטות shochtos אפילו afilu לכתחילה. lechatchila. Okay, that even
women even לכתחילה lechatchila could be שוחטות. shochtos. דהתנן dehasnan שחטו shachatu
בדיעבד bediavad משום דבעי למסקי mishum deba'ei lemisky טמאים. temeim. The only
language of if they slaughtered it's good refers to the טמא tamei
people. דלכתחילה לא delechatchila lo לא. lo. But that they shouldn't because
of a concern they might get the meat טמא tamei or they
might, okay, ולא קאמר משום דבעי למסקי נשים דתני רישא. velo ka'amar
mishum deba'ei lemisky nashim detani reisha. Okay. So women can even be
שוחטות shochtos לכתחילה lechatchila even for קרבנות. korbanot. מכאן תשובה למה שכתבו
בהלכות ארץ ישראל דנשים לא ישחטו מפני שדעתן קלה. mikan teshuvah lema
shekasvu behilchos eretz yisrael denashim lo yishchatu mipnei sheda'atan kalah. So this
is a rejection of this thing that appeared in this book called
הלכות ארץ ישראל, Hilchos Eretz Yisrael, which was a questionable provenance of
where it was coming from, what it was, it was probably coming
from some type of a, you know, more Kabbalistic or whatever, you
know, type of a pietistic group. Anyway, in that book it wrote,
women shouldn't שחט. shechting Now they weren't talking about קרבנות, korbanot, they
were talking about שחט shecht for like normal, you know, meat purposes.
Oh, because they you know they can't be trusted, women. So that's
what he's talking about, it's מפורש mefurash that they can even לכתחילה
lechatchila שחט shachted, even
קרבנות. korbanot. Okay. ועוד כתב בהן שחט ולא בירך ve'od kasav bahen
shachat velo berach and just to prove you that that book is
full of חומרות, chumros, that the book also says if somebody did
a שחיטה shechitah without making the ברכה, berachah, וערום ששחט שחיטתו פסולה.
ve'arum sheshachat shechitasto pesulah. If somebody was naked when they שחט, shachted
it invalidates the שחיטה. shechitah. Obviously that's not true. You have kosher
meat, it was שחט properly, okay. You should have made the ברכה
berachah whatever, it doesn't make the שחיטה shechitah invalid. ונראה שהם חומרות
בעלמא שהיה אומר אותם החכם שכתב הלכות ארץ ישראל. venireh shehem chumros
be'alma shehayah omer osam hechacham shekasav hilchos eretz yisrael. Whoever wrote that
book, they're just חומרות, chumros, they're not real הלכה halachah and so
on. Okay, so you see that interesting tension between whether actually from
a formal, from an actual like, you know, strict halachic perspective women
are actually permitted to do something, but then the מחמיר machmir position
is to say, no, no, no, we can't have women do these
things.
Okay. Anyway, so that's a good question. So in תוספות, Tosfos, in
the Ashkenazi, you know, period of the ראשונים, Rishonim, women were definitely
much more involved in society and in business and so on, you
know, and that led to תוספות Tosfos sort of, you know, addressing
certain הלכה halachah questions. Can women be, how do you deal with
the fact that women sometimes are in ייחוד yichud with non-Jews because
for business reasons? Can women, you know, make a ברכה berachah on
מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא? mitzvas asei shehazman grama? You have a lot
of תוספות Tosfos about women that reflected their greater, you know, their
more sort of serious standing within society, public standing within society, I
should say. Whether actually women were שוחטות, shochtos, right? It sounds like
it. It sounds like תוספות Tosfos is like feels like he has
to make this point for some practical reason, but I don't know
if we have any evidence that they were actually שוחטות, shochtos, but
you know, so I don't anyway. Okay, now by the way, I
should say that תוספות Tosfos has got a real problem here about
this case and about טמא. tamei. Because the question is, how טמא
tamei are you and where are you standing? And תוספות Tosfos says,
you know, there's certain טמא tamei people that can't even be in
the עזרת נשים. ezras nashim. So תוספות Tosfos says, what do you
think? You have a knife that's 135 אמות amos long, 200 feet
long? Like if you can't stand in the עזרת נשים, ezras nashim,
how do you get some טמא tamei people can be here but
some cannot, depending on your level of טומאה tumah or whatever. So
תוספות Tosfos suggests, well maybe you're standing here and you've got like,
you know, that the only reason, you know, the problem here is
that this is the normal entrance. So we don't have like a
zone, a certain, you know, a radius around. You can't be in
the עזרת נשים, ezras nashim, that's part of the structure and that's
the way you get in. So if you're a certain טמא tamei
person you can't be there, but you might be able to be
here and you have a little doorway and a little opening and
you put your קרבן korban right there or something like that. So
תוספות Tosfos deals with the logistical problem about if you're, you know,
if you're standing here we get it, but if you're not allowed
in the עזרת נשים, ezras nashim, then where exactly are you standing?
And he tries to figure that out.
Even if you're on the outside even if you're all the way
up against it.
Yeah, yeah. Okay, so we'll end here for now.